Finding Aid for Gardner Ackley Papers, 1936-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gardner Ackley Papers 1936-1999
Ackley, Gardner.
20 microfilms
1 oversize folders
36.5 linear feet
Professor of economics, University of Michigan, government official, and U.S. Ambassador to Italy. Correspondence, speeches, and memos, relating to Ackley's work as presidential adviser and member of President's Council of Economic Advisers during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations; reports and other papers, 1944-1945, concerning his work with U. S. Office of Price Administration; papers, 1950-1953, concerning his career as assistant director of U. S. Office of Price Stabilization; and miscellaneous research notes and University of Michigan course materials.
85576 Aa 2; Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection has been donated to the library in multiple accessions beginning in 1972 by Gardner Ackley (Donor No. 5205 ). Additional materials came from Mrs. Ackley and the Ackley family in 2005 and 2011.
The collection is open for research, except for microfilm rolls in box 23 which are for staff use only.
(Hugh) Gardner Ackley was born in Indianapolis, Indiana on June 30, 1915. In 1936, Ackley received his baccalaureate degree from Western State Teachers College (now Western Michigan University) in Kalamazoo, Michigan. In 1937, a master's degree was conferred upon Ackley by the University of Michigan and in 1940 he received a doctoral degree from the same institution.
In 1939 and 1940, Ackley was an instructor at Ohio State University, returning to teach at the University of Michigan in late 1940. Throughout the Second World War he served as a member of the government in Washington. From 1941 to 1942, and again from 1944 to 1946 he worked at the Office of Price Administration. In 1943 and 1944 he was assigned to the Office of Strategic Services. Concluding his wartime service, Mr. Ackley returned to the University of Michigan where he resumed his academic career in the Department of Economics.
Ackley returned to government service in 1951, serving for two years as the assistant director of the Office of Price Stabilization. After completing this assignment he once again returned to Ann Arbor to carry on scholarly pursuits.
Gardner Ackley left Ann Arbor for Washington for the third time in August 1962 when President John Kennedy named him as a member of the Council of Economic Advisors. He served as a member of the council until November 14, 1964, when President Lyndon Johnson named him the new chairman of the CEA. Early in 1968, Mr. Ackley left the council to become ambassador to Italy, a post he held until 1969. After returning from Italy, Ackley again resumed his academic career at the University of Michigan.
From 1969 until 1984 Ackley was the Henry Carter Adams University Professor of Political Economy at the University of Michigan. During this same period, he served on many national commissions and councils devoted to economic issues. He was a member of the Trilateral Commission from 1977 to 1983 and during 1978-1979 he was a member of the Advisory Council on Social Security. He also served as president of the American Economics Association during 1982.
Among his many honors, Ackley received the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award at the University of Michigan in 1976 and he was also elected a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Science. Ackley has been professor emeritus since 1984.
Gardner Ackley died February 12, 1998.
The Gardner Ackley papers document the career of one of the most influential economists of his time. As a researcher, teacher, and especially as an advisor to United States presidents and various government agencies Ackley helped formulate the direction of governmental economic policy. This collection reflects those activities. Ackley's papers arrived at the Bentley Library in four accessions: 1972 (boxes 1-23), 1988 (boxes 24-28), 2005 (boxes 29-36), and 2011 (boxes 37-38). Generally, papers from the first accession relate to his earlier career, those from the 1988 accession relate to his later career, and those from 2005 from all phases of his professional life. The 2011 accession consists mainly of photographs and other personal materials.
The collection is divided into twelve series: Office of Price Administration/Office of Price Stabilization files; President's Council of Economic Advisors files; University of Michigan files; Professional Correspondence; Meetings and Conferences; Speeches, Journal Articles, Letters to the Editor, Chronological correspondence, Clipping file, Columns and unpublished writings, US Ambassador to Italy, 1968-1969, Later career, and Personal: Photographs, Scrapbooks, etc.
Subjects:
Ackley, Gardner.; Council of Economic Advisers (U.S.); Economics.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; United States. Office of Price Administration.; United States. Office of Price Stabilization.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subject: Visual Materials
Ackley, Gardner.; Council of Economic Advisers (U.S.); Economic policy--United States.; Government officials--United States.; International relations--Italy.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre:
Photographs.
- Office of Price Administration/Office of Price Stabilization
  Office of Price Administration/Office of Price Stabilization. Those interested in Ackley's activities during World War II should consult folders under "Office of Price Administration". In addition to analyses of price levels of specific commodities during World War II these files contain studies of war profits of major American corporations. Ackley left the Office of Price Administration in 1946 but returned there in 1951. By that time, the agency had been renamed the Office of Price Stabilization. Hence, Office of Price Stabilization files for the years 1951-1953 contain similar material to the earlier Office of Price Administration files. Speeches and articles by Ackley during the early 1950s are also included under "Office of Price Stabilization".
  - Office of Price Administration Studies, etc.
    - War Profit Studies: Profits of 1753 large industrial corporations 1939-1941 (no. 1) (Box 1)
    - Profits of 200 important war contractors 1939-1941 (no. 2) (Box 1)
    - Two part study (no. 3)
      - Comparative Profits of 200 War, Contractors and 1559 other large industrial corporation (Pt. I) (Box 1)
      - Profits of consolidated corporations and subsidiaries 1939-1941 (Pt. II) (Box 1)
    - Corporate Profits for the first six months of 1942 (no. 4) (Box 1)
    - Price control report: The effectiveness of Price Control (to October 1942) (no. 13) (Box 1)
    - Price control report: the relation between Price Movements and the extent of control (to October 10, 1942) (no. 14) (Box 1)
    - Price control report: One Year of retail price control May 1942-May 1943 (no. 15) (Box 1)
    - Wholesale and Retail prices from January 1939 (Box 1)
      (published February 1943)
    - Consumer-price index for moderate income families in large cities (Box 1)
  - Office of Price Administration Subject files
    - Price Control Information 1943-1946, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Memorandum file January-May 1945 (Box 1)
    - Rebuttal to the Congressional Testimony of the National Retail Dry Goods Association March 1946 (Box 1)
    - Financial reporting forms (Box 1)
    - Price policy 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    - Formulas for establishing prices (Box 1)
    - Brief regarding Sulfuric Acid, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Price control, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Scrap metal (Box 1)
    - Brass and Bronze Ingot (Box 1)
    - Copper and Copper alloy scrap (Box 1)
    - Scrap metal miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Frequency distribution of 145 commodity lines September 1942 (Box 1)
  - Office of Price Stabilization
    - Reading file January-June 1952 (Box 1)
    - Material on Capenhart Formula (Box 1)
    - Price control information 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - Price control information August 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Report of Attorney General regarding possible monopolistic effects of Defense Production Act of 1950 (Box 2)
    - Inflation (Box 2)
    - Price Control Information 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Suspension of controls (Box 2)
    - Administrative History, Economic Stabilization Agency September 1950-January 1951 (Box 2)
    - Speeches of Michael V. DiSalle (Box 2)
    - Operational History papers (Box 2)
    - Memos 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Price Rollbacks (Box 2)
    - Analysis of Commodities Selling Below Ceiling Price November 1951 (Box 2)
    - Draft Standards on Basic Metals (Box 2)
    - Gardner Ackley: Speeches 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Gardner Ackley: Public Appearances 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Information regarding Steel Industry (Box 3)
    - Notes on Congressional Reports and Debates (Box 3)
    - Operational History Papers (Box 3)
    - The Problem of Price-Wage Coordination 1950-1953 (Box 3)
    - Price Control Information 1950-1953 (Box 3)
    - Information relating to Alan Valentine (Box 3)
    - Information on Price standards 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Price Control Information and Memorandums 1950-1953 (Box 3)
    - Marven H. Bernstein. Administrative History of the Economic Stabilization Agency September 1950-January 1951 and comments (Box 3)
    - Rationale for price control 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Office of Price Information: Summary of orders May 1951-March 1953 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Relaxation of Controls:
      - General (Box 3)
      - Apparel (Box 3)
      - Redding, burlap, cattlehides (Box 3)
      - Cigars (Box 3)
      - Coal (Box 3)
      - Fats and Oils (Box 3)
      - Horsehides, radios and television (Box 3)
      - Shoes and Leather, soft surface floor coverings (Box 4)
      - Textiles, Vitrified Chinaware, handmade glassware (Box 4)
      - Wastepaper, wool and related fibers (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Shortages, Inflation and National Planning (Box 4)
    - Defense Spending (Box 4)
    - Inflation (Box 4)
    - Information regarding Price Levels (Box 4)
    - Price control information 1950-1952 (Box 4)
    - Reading file 1951-August 1952, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Paper on "Statistics in Price Control" by Gardner Ackley, delivered December 27, 1951 to the American Statistical Association (Box 4)
    - Text of Gardner Ackley Speech made May 3, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Gardner Ackley speech file (Box 4)
    - Gardner Ackley speech notes (Box 4)
    - History Project and Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- President's Council of Economic Advisers
  The President's Council of Economic Advisors series documents Ackley's various activities within the council first as a member and then as chairman. This series is further divided into a number of sub-series. These sub-series are described here in the order in which they appear in the contents list. To begin, "Topical Files" are alphabetically arranged and document a wide range of economic and political subjects of interest to the council. The largest of the sub-series, "Speeches and Presentations", is chronologically arranged and includes speeches by Ackley at various functions. In most cases, the location and title of the speech is included as part of the folder title. Transcripts of interviews with Ackley on television and radio precede another large sub-series, "Meetings of the CEA". The meetings are subdivided into cabinet, governmental and non-governmental meetings. All three types are chronologically arranged and a brief description of the subject of the meeting is usually included in the contents list. A sub-series of "Memoranda" follows. Memoranda is divided into memos to the President, general memos, and memos to the White House staff. Each of these groups is chronologically arranged. Topics of the memoranda are only rarely included in the contents list. The "Correspondence" sub-series follows and is alphabetically arranged by correspondent. "News Media Articles, Interviews and Invitations" concludes the CEA series. News articles are arranged alphabetically by the name of the newspaper or magazine.
  In 1976, a positive microfilm copy of portions of Gardner Ackley's Council of Economic Advisors papers (boxes 5-18 (part)) was filmed for the Lyndon Johnson Presidential Library. The Bentley Library retains the negative microfilm (box 23). The donor requested that no additional copies of the film be made without his permission.
  - Topical Files
    - Agriculture
      - Cotton (Box 4)
      - Dairy Program (Box 4)
      - Food and Fiber Commission (Box 4)
      - Food Industry (Box 4)
      - Food Marketing Commission (Box 4)
      - (Sec.) Freeman's Reports to the President (Box 4)
      - Income (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Rice (Box 4)
      - Soybeans (Box 4)
      - Wheat and Feed Grains (Box 4)
    - Council of Economic Advisers Budget Request for 1967 (Box 4)
    - Election (Presidential) 1964
      - Democratic Platform (Box 4)
      - Inauguration (Box 4)
      - National Independent Committee for President Johnson and Senator Humphrey (Box 4)
    - Economic Growth (Box 5)
    - Economy (state of) June 1966 (Box 5)
    - Employment Act of 1946-Twentieth Anniversary Symposium 1966 (Box 5)
    - Federal Credit Programs (Committee on) (Box 5)
    - Federal-State-Local Fiscal Relationships (Box 5)
    - Government Organization (Task Force on) (Box 5)
    - Guideposts (Box 5)
    - Harvard Business Review-Gardner Ackley's response to article "Wages and Prices by Formula?" by Arthur Burns, March-April 1965 (Box 5)
    - Imports (study of) (Box 5)
    - Income maintenance (Task Force on) (Box 5)
    - Income Policy Proposal (Box 5)
    - International Conferences-staff expenses (Box 5)
    - International Political Crisis-Cuba and Berlin (Box 5)
    - Kennedy Assassination-Immediate Reactions (Box 5)
    - Monetary Policy 1962-1965, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Mortgage Financing (Task Force on) (Box 5)
    - Nominees-William A. Jump Foundation (Box 5)
    - Pollution Abatement (Task Force on) (Box 5)
    - Presidential Appointments
      - Automation Commission (Box 5)
      - Civil Aeronautics Board (Box 5)
      - Commerce Department (Box 5)
      - Council of Economic Advisors, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Council of Economic Advisors, Gardner Ackley (Box 5)
      - Financial Agencies, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Federal Trade Commission (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - Office of Economic Opportunity (Box 5)
      - Tariff Commission (Box 5)
    - Presidential Meetings
      - Regarding balance of payments February 18, 1965 (Box 5)
      - With Congressional Leadership July 18-19, 1966 (Box 5)
      - With Congressional Leadership 1967 (Box 6)
      - With Labor Leaders August 31, 1966 (Box 6)
      - With Labor Leaders March 9, 1967 (Box 6)
      - With Governors of States September 23, 1966 (Box 6)
      - With Governors of U.S. territories March 18, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Presidential Speeches-Drafts and Statements (Box 6)
    - Presidential Speech before the Business Council December 6, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Press Conference materials (Box 6)
    - Press Releases
      - Council of Economic Advisors (Box 6)
      - Resignations (Box 6)
    - Speeches
      - James S. Duesenberry (Box 6)
      - Arthur M. Okun (Box 6)
    - Task Forces 1968
      - Environment. (Box 6)
      - Housing and Urban Development (Box 6)
      - Manpower (Box 6)
      - New Towns (Box 6)
      - Rural Poverty (Box 6)
      - Rural-Urban Migration (Box 6)
    - Taxes
      - Tax Message 1961 (Box 6)
      - Depreciation Guidelines (Box 6)
      - 1962 Reduction (Box 6)
      - Treasury Program November 1962-January 1963 (Box 6)
      - 1963 Tax Bill
        - General (Box 6)
        - Description (Box 6)
        - Statements regarding 1963 Tax Bill (Box 6)
        - Senate Finance Committee Hearings November 12, 1963
          - Tax Tables (Box 6)
          - Direct versus Indirect Taxation (Box 6)
          - Council of Economic Advisors Testimony (Box 6)
          - Questions and Answers (Box 6)
          - Memos and Comments (Box 6)
        - Tax Legislation in Ways and Means Committee 1963 (Box 6)
      - 1963 Miscellaneous (Box 6)
      - Presidential Statements on Tax Program 1963-1964 (Box 6)
      - Statements regarding 1964 tax cut (Box 7)
      - Effects of 1964 tax cut 1964-1967, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Tax increase 1967 (Box 7)
    - Troika 1961-1968, 8 folders (Box 7)
    - United Kingdom.-Financial Crisis November 1964 (Box 7)
    - Universities-Utilization of Universities for Developing Policy (Box 7)
    - Wages and Prices
      - Policy (Box 7)
      - (Task Force on) (Box 7)
  - Speeches and Presentations
    - Americans For Democratic Action, New York City. "Performance and Prospects of the United States Economy" October 13, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Washington February 4, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Fiscal Policy Seminar, Harvard. Subject: Economic Report March 4, 1963 (Box 7)
    - American Bankers' Association, Princeton, N.J. "Bank Structure and Regulation" March 7, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Economic Club of Pittsburgh, "The Federal Budget and Economic Growth" March 13, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Seminar at University of Maryland, "Italian Post-War Economic Growth and Its Possible Implications for U.S. Policy." March 14, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Dedication, Whittemore School of Business and Economics, University of New Hampshire. "A Dynamic Economy: Its Challenge .To Business." March 28, 1963 (Box 7)
    - The Exchequer Club, Washington April 17, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Insurance Investment Officers, Washington April 17, 1963 (Box 7)
    - AFL-CIO Labor Educator Conference, Washington. "Shorter Work Week" April 18, 1963 (Box 7)
    - World Affairs Council, Albany, New York. "What Kind of World Can We Afford" April 23, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Midwest Economic Association, St. Louis. "Economic Policies of the Kennedy Administration" April 26, 1963, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Secretary of Labor's Conference for Labor Editors, Washington. "The State and Outlook of The Economy" May 20, 1963 (Box 8)
    - School of Business Administration, University of Michigan. "The Federal Budget and a Dynamic Economy" May 21, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Treasurers Club of New York City June 5, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Ford Foundation Workshop on Economic Growth, Pittsburgh. Subject-Growth Policies June 28, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Western Economic Association, San Francisco. "Current Economic Policy" August 22-23, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Conference on Money and Banking, Columbia University. "Current Issues in Economic Policy" September 6, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Vermont-New Hampshire School of Banking, Hanover, New Hampshire. "Our National Economy: Present Situation and Outlook" September 8, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Annual Conference, Tax Executives Institute, Chicago. "Tax Reduction for full Employment and Growth" September 16, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Public Issues Conference for Elected Union officials, Williamsburg, Virginia. Sponsored by the Brookings Institution: October 10-11, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Guest lecture, Pennsylvania State University. "U.S. Economic Growth: Is it Good Enough?" October 21, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Annual Business Outlook Luncheon, Metropolitan Washington. Board of Trade January 28, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Federal Home Loan Bank Board January 30, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo Management Association, Kalamazoo, Michigan. "Jobs and Prices: .Our Economic Agenda for 1964" April 7, 1964 (Box 8)
    - University of Michigan. "Automation and Unemployment" April 8, 1964 (Box 8)
    - American University Honorary Economic Society. May 1, 1964 (Box 8)
    - National Educational Association, Washington. Subject: Poverty, Education and the National Economy May 3, 1964 (Box 8)
    - American Bankers Association Monetary Conference, Vienna, Austria. May 19, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Woman's National Democratic Club, Washington. May 28, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Forecasters Club of New York. "The Impact of the Government's Economic Program Upon the Business Outlook" June 26, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Annual convention of the National Business League and National Bankers Association, Washington. "Greeting" August 26, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Conference of University Professors sponsored by the American Bankers Association, Princeton. August 29, 1964 (Box 8)
    - New England Conference on the Opportunities and Problems of Defense Conversion, Boston. "American Economic Policies--The Goals and Priorities" September 21, 1964, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Annual Conference of the Center for Economic Projections, Washington. "The Role of Government--Federal, State, Local" September 25, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Governor's (California) Advisory Panel on the Aerospace and Electronics Industries, Los Angeles. September 30, 1964 (Box 8)
    - University of California, Berkeley. "The Effects of the Tax Cut" October 1, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Annual Western Briefing, Conference on Government Contracts, sponsored by the Federal Bar Association, San Francisco October 2, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Sunday Breakfast Club, Philadelphia. "The Task of Sustaining Prosperity" October 7, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Annual Meeting, The Association of Edison Illuminating Companies, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia. "Our Expanding Economy" October 21, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Seventh Office of Manpower, Automation and Training Seminar on Manpower Policy and Program, Department of Labor. "Policies for the Promotion of Economic Growth" January 28, 1965 (Box 8)
    - State of the Nation, Silver Quill Dinner, Washington. February 4, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Luncheon and dinner, Economic Club of Chicago. February 25, 1965 (Box 8)
    - University of Chicago. February 25, 1965, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Mortgage Bankers Association, National Mortgage Conference, New York City. "Economic Policies and Problems in 1965" March 8, 1965, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Overseas Writers Club Luncheon, Washington. March 16, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Princeton University Conference on the Economic Report. March 19, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Investment Bankers Association of America, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia. May 6, 1965 (Box 9)
    - The Business Council Meeting, Hot Springs, Virginia. May 7, 1965, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - American Association of University Women, Arlington Branch, Arlington, Virginia. May 11, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Annual Convention of the National Association of Mutual Savings Bank, Washington. "The New Economics for the Great Society" May 17, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Annual meeting, Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia. "The American Economy: Problems and Prospects" May 26, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Global Strategy Discussions, Naval War College, Newport, Rhode Island. "Economic Considerations in National Strategy" June 8, 1965 (Box 9)
    - World Congress on Marketing of the American Marketing Association, New York City. "New Trends in Economic Policy" June 16, 1965 (Box 9)
    - White House Dinner June 22, 1965 (Box 9)
    - British-American Parliamentary Group, Houses of Parliament. July 6, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Luncheon, United States-Japan Trade Council, Washington. July 12, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Arkansas Economic Education Workshop, Little Rock, Arkansas. August 4, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Annual Economic Outlook Luncheon, American Statistical Association, Philadelphia. September 9, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Senior Seminar in Foreign Policy, Department of State. September 22, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Governor's Conference on Unemployment in California, Monterey, California. October 2, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Sales and Marketing Executives Association, San Francisco. October 4, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Business Council of Washington, Hot Springs, Virginia. October 16, 1965 (Box 9)